Brown family papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Brown Family Papers
1857-1955
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Brown family
0.50 linear feet (1 box)
Biographical Sketch
The matriarch of this family was Sarah W. Kendall Brown, the daughter of John Kendall of Ohio and later of New Lebanon, New York. She married Henry L. Brown (d. 1892) of New Lebanon. They had four sons: Harvey L. (b. 1872), Walter Throop Kendall (b. 1874), Howard P. (born 1878), and Avery E. (b. 1882). The family relocated to Pittsfield, Massachusetts and eventually to Short Beach, located in Branford, Connecticut.
Avery remained in Pittsfield where he worked as a mechanic at the City Garage & Sales Company. Howard studied to be an actuary and worked for the Veterans Administration in Washington, DC. He and his wife Beatrice brought up her nephew David after the boy’s parents died.
Walter T.K. Brown married L. Maude Salmon (b. 1870) of Hudson, New York. They had three sons: Kendall (1908-1989), and Throop C. and George, twins born in 1910 in Pittsfield, Mass. When Walter joined the Winchester Fire Arms firm in New Haven, the family moved to Branford.
Scope and Content
The collection was purchased from a Philadelphia dealer, who arranged the letters by recipient. In keeping with archival practice, they were re-arranged by letter writer and then further organized by generation. Incoming letters precede outgoing.
John Kendall’s papers include a letter from Rochester, New York in which the writer related hearing a speech by “a colored man”, 1867, and another letter regarding a court case between Kendall and a Mr. Clark, 1891. His daughter Ellen is represented by two letters from relatives, 1894, 1907, and some genealogical notes about the Avery family, undated.
Kendall’s daughter Sarah W. married Henry L. Brown in 1870 and the first letter among her papers is one from Henry regarding their upcoming wedding. The bulk of her incoming correspondence is from cousins in Michigan. Of interest is a letter from Phyllis Kihn of the Connecticut Historical Society regarding Throop family genealogy. Sarah’s correspondence continues until 1945.
Henry L. Brown appears to have been a lawyer in New Lebanon, New York. His correspondents include business associates, 1887-1888, and his son Walter, 1890.
Harvey L. Brown and his wife, Lulu, wrote to Sarah W.K. Brown about brother Avery’s problems supporting himself and Harvey bragged about his daughter Dorothy Deborah winning an essay contest at Bridgeport High School.
The majority of Walter T.K. Brown’s letters are to his son, Kendall who was a merchant seaman in 1932. Walter discussed with his son the China and Japan question, a court case Walter eventually won, the Lindberg kidnapping, and politics. In 1907, Walter received notice that he had been elected an Associate of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers. Walter’s wife, L. Maude Brown, has correspondence dating from 1907-1955. Her papers also include some religious writings, presumably from her mother, and her parents’ marriage certificate, 1857. She received letters of congratulations on the birth of her twins, George and Throop in 1910 and more congratulations when the family moved into a new house in Pittsfield. The bulk of her incoming correspondence is from friends, nieces and nephews.
Howard Brown’s correspondence dates from 1926-1934 and includes letters written by his wife Beatrice to their mother, Sarah W.K. Brown. The missives are chatty and filled with family and gardening news. One letter provides a detailed description of making “french fried potatoes”. Other topics covered include China (1927), a visit to Washington by Charles Lindberg, and receiving a new frigidare for their apartment.
Avery wrote from Pittsfield from 1924-1933 to his mother, his brother Walter and his nephews Throop and George. He provided descriptions and a few sketches of the cottage in which he was living, discussed how automobile insurance had reduced the number of cars on the road, and how electricity was not popular in Pittsfield. He also addressed settling his Aunt Ellen Kendall’s estate.
Kendall Brown, son of Maude and Walter Brown and the merchant mariner, wrote three letters to his mother, 1931-1933 that are included in this collection. He wrote on board ship while traveling to the China Sea from Japan on the U.S.S. President Wilson, and to Havana, Cuba and Kobe, Japan on the U.S.S. President Harrison. Kendall’s papers include some membership cards from various nautical organizations and several samples of short stories he tried to get published.
Throop C. Brown, another son of Maude and Walter, attended Dean Academy in Franklin, Massachusetts; his twin brother George did not. Throop’s letters home, 1930-1931, consistently addressed the topics of laundry (he sent it home), “eatables” sent by his mother, and playing hockey. Occasionally he spoke about his grades and studying. Two of George’s letters, addressed from Fort Devens, Massachusetts in 1943, mentioned a Joe Louis boxing exhibition, a movie he saw, and his assessment of his commanding officer.
Finally, Harvey Brown’s daughter Dorothy Deborah sent two letters to her grandmother, L. Maude Brown. One discussed her trip to Washington DC, 1927, and the other was a thank you for Christmas gifts, 1928
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Brown, Avery, b. 1882.; Brown, George, b. 1910.; Brown, Harvey L., d. 1892.; Brown, Howard P., b. 1878.; Brown, Kendall R., 1908-1989.; Brown, Laura Maude, b. 1870; Brown, Throop, 1910-1995.; Brown, Sarah W. Kendall, b. ca. 1842.; Brown, Walter Throop Kendall, b. 1874.
Contents:
- Papers
  - John Kendall incoming correspondence, 1867, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ellen Kendall correspondence, 1894, 1907, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sarah W. Kendall Brown correspondence, 1870-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Henry L. Brown correspondence, 1887-1890 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Harvey L. and Lulu Brown correspondence, 1927-1928, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Walter Throop Kendall Brown papers, 1902-1935 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - L. Maude Brown papers, 1857, 1907-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
  - Howard and Beatrice Brown correspondence, 1926-1943 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - Avery Brown correspondence, 1924-1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Kendall R. Brown papers, 1930-1947 (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Throop C. Brown correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - George Brown correspondence, 1925-1945 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dorothy Deborah Brown letters, 1927, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Assorted non-family papers (Box 1, Folder 25)